Si nous le jouons directement, nous avons ceci.
Bonjour, c'est Alex Citibo.
Bienvenue au second épisode de Making Music in Shadotoy.
Dans l'un des premiers épisodes, nous avons regardé des basiques
de l'utiliser le sound buffer en Shadotoy
et comment utiliser pour créer des notes
avec différentes fréquences, timbres, panneaux.
Nous avons joué avec des formes de la waveform,
incluant la modulation de la fréquence,
et nous avons utilisé pour créer un syntho simple
et une mélodie simple.
Aujourd'hui, j'aimerais couvrir un peu plus bas
pour savoir pourquoi est FM
un outil convenant
pour faire le sound design en Shadotoy.
Comment pouvons-nous comprendre ces paramètres
et comment pouvons-nous utiliser pour créer
des instruments intéressants ?
Aujourd'hui, nous allons créer un pad et un syntho lead
avec des mélodies pour ces instruments.
Avant de commencer, je vous encourage
à essayer de couvrir avec moi si c'est possible pour vous.
La raison pour laquelle vous allez avoir
beaucoup plus d'outils.
Si vous n'avez pas besoin d'autre chose,
vous pouvez aller à Shadotoy.com
et ouvrir un nouveau shader
avec le sound tab et vous allez bien.
Si vous n'avez pas perdu à quel point
vous pouvez toujours poser le vidéo
ou vous pouvez juste suivre le lien
dans la description
pour le code que nous allons obtenir
à la fin de l'épisode d'aujourd'hui.
Allons-y !
Aujourd'hui, nous allons
travailler avec la modulation de la fréquence.
Qu'est-ce que ce que c'est ?
C'est quand vous avez une waveforme répétie
mais cette waveforme est répétie
avec une période différente
selon le temps.
Vous avez une fréquence instantanée
FFT
fréquence instantanée
et puis vous avez un signal
On va utiliser une fonction de signes
ici, comme une waveforme
vous pouvez utiliser d'autres formes de waveforms
et ce sera le sign de la phase.
Qu'est-ce que la fonction de phase
devrait être utilisé ?
C'est une phase de T ici.
Qu'est-ce que la fonction de phase
devrait être utilisé
pour obtenir la fréquence qu'on veut ?
La profondeur qu'on a besoin
est que la durée de temps
de la fonction de phase
devrait être d'une pi
fois FFT.
Je vais définir
ce micro ici
comme la dernière fois
on va utiliser le constant beaucoup.
La phase devrait être
l'intégral
de cette phase prime.
La phase de T
devrait être l'intégral
de pi x FFT
de T.
Il peut être l'intégral
ou il peut être un constant
de la phase prime.
On va voir des espèces spéciales.
D'abord, on va voir
ce qui se passe si nous avons
une fréquence constante.
En ce cas, c'est assez
obvious
mais on va faire la calculation.
La phase prime
de T
sera 2 pi
fois FFT.
Si nous intégrons
cette phase
de T
qui est de pi x FFT
de T plus un constant
donc le signal
à la fin
sera
le signe
de pi x FFT
plus un constant.
Ici
le constant c'est juste
la phase offset
donc vous pouvez juste le mettre
si vous voulez.
Nos yeux
ne peuvent vraiment détecter
si il y a une phase shift
ou pas.
On va voir
ce qui se passe
si nous avons
une fréquence constante.
Ça se passe
si nous avons une variation synésoidale.
On va introduire
une
fréquence carrière
appelée FC.
On va introduire
une fréquence modulée
appelée FM
et
on va
introduire
une fréquence
de déviation
et ça
sera appelé DF.
FFT
sera
une fC
plus
un DF
de cosine
de 2 pi
x T.
J'ai utilisé un cosine
pour un changement.
Ce que nous voulons
c'est que la phase prime
de T
est 2 pi
de pi
ou tout ça.
Qu'est-ce qu'on doit mettre
en phase de T ?
Nous avons
la première termine
qui est 2 pi x FC x T
Et puis, let's integrate the second term.
Let me make this a little bit clearer by distributing the two parts.
So how do we integrate cosine of constant times t?
Le constant est out.
Donc nous devons diviser par 2pi times fm.
Et puis l'intégral de cosine est sine.
Nous allons obtenir 2pi times tf over 2pi times fm times sine f2pi times fm times t.
C'est évidemment le 2pi que l'on annonce.
Et c'est ce que l'on obtient.
Donc à la fin, notre signal sera 2pi times fc times t plus df over fm times sine f2pi times fm times t.
Donc c'est la modulation de fréquence quand la fonction modulée est sine.
Ce que l'on peut introduire est l'index de modulation, iom.
C'est ce que j'ai introduit la dernière fois.
C'est juste df over fm.
Alors que nous n'avons que de l'IOM ici.
Nous allons défendre un macro pour tout ceci.
Comment l'on fait de la modulation de fréquence avec fc, fm et iom?
Nous allons rétablir un signal de fc times 2pi times fc times t plus iom times sine f2pi times fm times t.
Je vais assumer que la t est définie dans le contexte.
Et j'ai mis des parenthèses autour de fc et fm et iom.
Juste en cas d'expressions. Parce que ce sera en ligne.
Nous allons défendre ceci.
Ce que j'aimerais faire maintenant, c'est de voir le spectre de ce son.
Alors, nous allons introduire un signal, juste comme la dernière fois,
qui nous retournons.
Et pour le signal, nous allons ajouter ce fm.
Nous allons essayer une wave de 1 kHz avec un modulateur de 100 Hz.
Et pour la no-modulation, je vais mettre une petite amplitude,
juste pour que ce soit pas trop obnoxieux.
Alors, j'ai ouvert un spectre analyzer.
Je ne sais pas ce que c'est, c'est un outil qui nous permet de voir
quelle frequencies sont présentes dans notre signal.
Ce que ça fait, c'est que ça écoute à l'outil de l'outil de l'étoile,
ça choque le signal dans deux portes de temps.
Et sur chaque port, ça décompose le signal comme un nombre de components sinusoidales.
Et ça nous choque l'amplitude de chaque component de ça.
Alors, si nous le mettons, maintenant, nous faisons un fm, mais nous n'avons pas de modulation,
parce que l'index de modulation est 0.
Donc, ce que nous devons faire, c'est une pure wave de signal.
Et c'est ce que nous avons.
Maintenant, si j'ai augmenté l'index de modulation,
qu'est-ce que vous pensez que ça va arriver ?
On va essayer.
C'est intéressant.
Ce que nous avons, c'est que la fréquence centrale reste à 1.000 Hz,
mais ensuite, nous avons des peaks, des components sinusodales,
à 900, 800, 700, et nous avons aussi des components à 1100, 1200, etc.
Maintenant, je réalise qu'il y a un peu d'issue dans mon code,
parce qu'on utilise un signe d'un grand nombre.
On va mettre le mod à 1.
On peut juste utiliser la fréquence,
et faire la même chose qu'ici,
pour que ça ne se débrouille après quelques secondes.
Maintenant, ce que vous pensez que ça va arriver,
si j'ai augmenté la fréquence de modulation.
On voit que la fréquence centrale était basée à 100 Hz,
si j'ai augmenté la fréquence de modulation à 120 Hz,
bien sûr, la fréquence centrale était basée à 100 Hz.
Qu'est-ce qui va arriver si j'ai augmenté la fréquence de modulation à 2 Hz?
Bien sûr, ça va aller jusqu'à 2 Hz.
Maintenant, ce que vous pensez que ça va arriver,
si j'ai augmenté la fréquence de modulation?
On va essayer ça.
On a un peu plus de pique.
La fréquence de modulation s'améliore,
à l'aide de notre signe.
Comme vous le voyez, ça s'améliore et s'améliore
et s'occupe de plus en plus de la fréquence.
On va mettre la fréquence de modulation à 2 Hz et à 100 Hz
et voir précisément ce qui se passe ici.
Si nous sommes au centre de la fréquence de modulation à 2 Hz,
nous avons un modulateur de 100 Hz et un index de modulation de 10 Hz.
On voit que la fréquence de modulation de modulation
...
100 Hz, donc nous pouvons interpréter ça comme, bon, les audibles sidebends
RFC plus ou moins, n times fn, for n is equal to about the index of modulation
That's not exactly, depending on where you cut, you can consider that it's a slightly wider thing but
that's a rule of thumb. Alright, before we move on, what do you think happens if the audible sideband
gets a negative frequency? For instance, let's try 500 Hz and with a 300 Hz modulation and 2 as an
index of modulation, so here, we've got 500 Hz, let's look at the lower sideband, so 500 minus 300
is 200, 200 minus 300 again is negative 100, so will the universe blow up or will something else happen?
Of course, what we will get is just a positive frequency at, well it should be minus 100 Hz, so we get plus 100 Hz
So that's what you see here and if you look closely, you will see that there is also a negative 400 which gets
reflected back to positive 400 and if we increase the index of modulation again, you get 700 and so on
So, negative frequencies get reflected back, in other words, we just have an absolute value here
Fantastic, I think that's really enlightening because this means that the spectrum of our signal, we have a very precise control over it
So when we will be doing some sound design, we will be able to control precisely what components are in our generated signal
So let's try the notes right now, now I want to move on to creating a pad, so let's create a pad, a very ethereal dreamy sound
I'm going to have its stereo, let's call it pad synth
And have it use a frequency and a time
So let's define a signal and return that signal, so what should we be doing to our signal?
Well, what we will be doing is just add a bunch of frequency components
All right, so you get the idea, so what should we be adding first?
One thing I like to have first is always a kind of solid body
A warm sound, which is kind of the root of our pad
Let's actually hear it right now, let's put on a 300 Hz
So you see that's a basic sound, but I don't know what to do
What we can do to make it a bit more interesting is add some modulation
So let's detune slightly the modulator from the carrier
And make it stereo
So now we get this, a slightly stereo effect
I'm not very fond of using 300 Hz here, so let me define a macro to get from a note number
To a frequency, last time I had my note numbers relative to the A440
But I like to have them related more to the middle C, which happens to be 90 Hz
So let's use that instead, we will be using a note number minus 9
Divided by 12
That will be the, that will be the, that will be the
12 tone equal temperament frequency for a note with a note number
Which is relative to middle C, so if we put N of 0 here, we should get middle C
Right, if you have perfect pitch, maybe you can notice that
Ok, so right now this does not sound like a pad at all
The problem with that is with the envelope, so let's define an envelope
Let's have it increase smoothly from 0 to 1
Over the course of, I don't know, let's say 5 tenths of a second
Right, we get some nice smooth increase
It's nice smooth increase in our signal
Let's make this a bit more interesting by adding some detuned stuff
Let's try, I don't know this
Maybe make this slightly less
Right, so we've got a very smooth, maybe a very warm body sound
What it kind of lacks is some personality
What I mean by personality is, when you get into a music mix
If you have only frequencies around 300 to 1 kHz
It will just get lost in the mix
So what we need to do is give it some, a bit higher frequencies
Very slight, but just so that it still can stick out
Even if we have a lot of masking around this center frequencies
So let's have another signal with a carrier
Which I would like it to be around 2 kHz
I don't want to do directly fc equals 2 kHz
Because then it won't be a multiple of f
So I want to round it to the closest multiple of f
And to do that, I will be doing f times round of 2000 divided by f
And now I can do fm of fcf
And what index of modulation should I use
Let's say I'd like to have about 1 kHz of frequency defiation
So it should be 1000 divided by the modulation frequency
So here we will be just using f
Let's listen to that
Right, so now we get some character, some personality
Right now it's pretty ugly
So we definitely need to add some more layering
As well as some modulation
I don't know, I'm really putting random numbers here
Let's have this a little lower
And let's have the index of modulation vary with time
Let's have, yeah just sign of t here
Maybe a bit faster
Right, that's basically the root of our signal
Maybe I can do some more modulation
Have it be a bit slower here
Like 2 times t
Or 1.9, I don't know
Minus
All right, what we can do then
Let's use it to create a chord
So how do we create a chord?
Well I'd like to have a 4 note chord
So let's have 4 frequencies
And add them to the signal
So we will just be having 6 plus equal
That's the nth of fs.xt
And the same for yz and w
And return sig
That's it
So now if we want to have a bad chord pattern
With just time in it
I will define a chord
Let's say I would like an A minor
With a B in it
So this will be A B C and E
I forgot a t here
And let's directly return pad chord of
N of chord
The frequencies of those notes
And t
So what happens then?
Right, this is getting somewhere
Ok, so let's pan those frequencies around
Let's just do it manually
So here the lowest note
Maybe I'd like to pan it a bit to the left
So let's say 0.8, 0.3
Then the middle note
Let's pan it completely to the left
Well, almost completely to the left
The second middle note
Almost completely to the right
And the last note
Slightly to the right
So what we get is
The extremes like the bass note
And highest note almost tucked in
To the center
And the rest all wider
Because no one really cares about the middle note
So we can put them really farther around
Let's hear that
This is getting spacey
One thing we can do
Is add some reverb
So we have a pad chord pattern
So let's call it a pad chord pattern verb
I'm saying reverb
It's not actually reverb
And fortunately a shader toy is not
Able to do all the stuff that you would be using
That you would be doing using usual digital signal processing
But what you can do is add a signal
With some delayed versions of it
And that's a kind of fake reverb
That is totally fine
So let's actually
So let's actually do that
Here
So we can have a pad chord pattern T
And then we can have
T minus 0.5
I don't know
Times 0.2
And that's just a delayed version of it
And let's shift
Let's swap the indices
And invert
One of the channels
So we get a more
More surprising kind of sound
Right now the chord pattern is very boring
Because we've got only one chord
So how do we go at defining
An actual chord pattern
Well, first thing I'd like to do
Is define a speed
A tempo for my song
So let's say ppm 100 beats per minute
And that would mean
That the beat duration should be
60 seconds divided by the number of beats per minute
So right now it should be a bit over half a second
And let's use that
To change up our chords
So our chord
Let's use a ternary operator
To say what chord we'd like to be using
So we will say if T is less than
4 times the beat duration
Then we will use this A minor
But then
What happens if it's not
Well it can be in the second bar
It can be in the third bar
And let's have it change 2 times
In the last bar
So we get 5 chords total
And now we just get creative
So one chord pattern that I liked
Was having
An F chord here
Let's put a D
Yeah let's put a D minor 7 here
So that's A, C, D, F
Then F major
Which will be F, A, C
And let's put a G on top
And then let's use a C major
With a D in it
G, C, D, E
And finally
Just change
Just change the C for a B
So we get
So we get a kind of G major with an E on top
Now if we play that directly we get this
A, C, D, E
Which is fine
But it's clicking
So what we need to do
Is make sure that
The notes actually restart
When we're changing chords
So let's define T current
B, T, F
So now we get the attack
But we don't have the decay
So let's have an envelope
For the decay
Float and
We need to make sure that the note goes down
To zero at the end of the note
So when should it be at zero
Well at four times beat two
And when should it be
Still at one
Well let's say at 3.5 times beat two
And now we should get this
Whoops
I have a sticker here
And I think we need to
Oh, I was actually not using
The chord pattern verb here
So yeah, let's try this
With a 1.5
1.5 beat delay
That's a bit longer, it's actually 2.75
Yeah, now if we want
Our chord pattern to repeat
We should set T equals mod
T 16 beat
But we also don't want it
Here we are using negative times
So when we are using negative times
We should set T equals mod
We don't want there to be any sound
So let's put T equals max T0
Otherwise when we are doing this
We will get the tail of the reverb
As if there had already been sound
Before
I'm not really fond of that reverb
Let's see if I can change it up a bit
So that it's a bit more fun
Let's have some fake early reflections
Here before any actual
Before any actual
Actual reverb
And then let's set the reverb 2.25
Yeah
In there
Let's go
All right, let's roll with this
Now I want to move on to making
A lead synth
Here we will be using the same kind of technique
So let's create a lead synth
Let's say it should have a certain frequency
And a certain time
Now what I'd really like to do
Is have it play with vibrato
So let's first create a basic sound
And then I'll show you the wrong way
And the right way to the vibrato
In shader toy
So
So now we've got this basic lead
Synth sound
Which is really just
Just this
And now let's say I want
The frequency
Let's say I want to add vibrato
So what I could do
Is say let's change up the frequency a bit
Let's say we
Multiply
Or we add something to it
And it should be
Like
0.2 of a semitone
So a semitone is about
0.06 times the frequency
And
Let's say we want to have
A 5 Hz vibrato
So this will be
20 cents of a semitone
And this will be
The amount of frequency
This is the wrong way to do it
I'll explain you why
Just a bit later
But let's hear
What it does
And how it sounds
Don't do that
That's awful
So yeah
So what's happening here
Well if you recall
Earlier I said
That
When we have some instantaneous frequency
The phase
The derivative of the phase
Should be 2 times f
So now
What's happening is
The actual phase we're using
When we're putting this
F into fm
The actual phase we're using
Is f of t times t
And that's
That's what the problem is
Because when we
Differentiate that with respect to time
We get f of t
Sure enough
But with a product rule
We also get
f' of t times t
And this guys
Is really problematic
Here f' of t
Will be a kind of
Cosine component
And it will be increasing
With respect to time
Increasing in amplitude
So that's why we get this
Stronger and stronger
Wobble
Yeah, don't do it
What is the right way to do it?
Well
What we want
Is for f of t
To be
Well it should be f0 plus
It's really basically the same formula as before
Plus cosine of 2pi
Times
Modulating frequency
Times time
So when we integrate it
We get that phase of t
Is f0 times t
Well 2pi sorry
2pi times f0 times t
Plus
df over fm
Times cosine
Times sine
2pi times fm
Times t
Except that now fm
Will be like 5 hertz
And f0
Will be
Well the frequency of our lead synth
And df
It should be
Something small
So yeah, this is the wrong way to do it
Let's not use that
Instead let's calculate
The phase using that formula
Let's do a function
For that
Call it vibrato phase
Have f0
df
And
Let's call it vibrato
So it's clear
We're talking about
The speed of vibrato
And
Let's even put
A semitone here
So you can say df
Will be 0.06 times f0
That is about
1 semitone
So let's multiply that by semitones
And
Then phase
Will be
This formula here
And where fm
Is vibrato
And return phase
Yeah, we need t here
And
So this is vibrato phase
Of
f
Let's have 0.2 semitones
5 hertz of vibrato
And t
But now we're getting onto a problem
Because our fm function
Doesn't get phase
It uses frequency
So yeah, whatever, let's define
A second macro
Which will be using phase
It's really simple
Let's call it fm2
Just replace fc times t
With pc
And fm times t
With pm
That's it
Let's use it
There's a problem here
And it has to do with the fact
That I used
2pi
This is actually modpc2pi
And modpm2pi
Right
So here now we're getting
A slight vibrato
I can increase it
To be more noticeable
But this is getting
Intasteful
So let's stick with that
We can also
Put some kind of envelope on our vibrato
And say
It should go from
It should start with no vibrato
And then increase
Up to its maximum
In about half a second
So now if you notice
We're getting no vibrato at the start
And some vibrato afterwards
Right
Let's make our lead sound more interesting
First thing I'd like to do
Is have
Some
Some layering
Right
This is still the body
Of this sound
Let's make it a bit harsher
Right so we get a bit
Wider spectrum
And then
Let's add some presence
So presence is
Like when you have a guitar amp
And you turn up the presence
It kind of turns up
A very specific frequency
To which our ear is very sensitive
Which is about 5 kHz
So let's
Have
A carrier frequency
At about 5 kHz
Let's do the same trick
As
Before
Let's round 5 kHz
To the nearest
Multiple of
The frequency
And
Have
The index of modulation
About 2 kHz
By F
And now
We want to make sure
To use FM2 again
Because
Because we are
Dealing with some vibrato
So we can't be using FC directly
Let's use the ratio
Which is just the integer ratio
Of
Carrier frequency
So we can be using
3x phase here
And phase
And index of modulation
Let's have it times 0.01
Right
So this is getting
This is getting much brighter
This is giving us
A nice sharp
Nice sharp sound
Maybe
All right
Let's have it
Let's have some more stuff in here
Okay
And now what we need to do
Is give it a bit of attack
And for that
We will be using
A very wide
A very wide signal
Actually we don't care about
We don't care about vibrato
For the attack
So let's just use
Our simple FM
Method
What we can do
Is
Around FC
To
Actually for this one
We don't even care about
If the
Components are actually multiples
Of the frequency or not
Because it will be decreasing so fast
So let's have exponential
Of minus 20
Times time
Here let's have an index of modulation
Of
10 kHz divided by F
And here it goes
Yeah
Yeah, that's a bit 3D
Actually let's run this
To multiple a bit
Yeah
All right
Now we can play a bit with the envelope
Of it
To make it
A bit
A bit more punchy
More plucky
So when you have an audio compressor
It's a volume knob
That goes
It turns down the loud sounds with some delay
And it's used creatively
In many mixes
Because due to that delay
It kind of adds
A wobbly
Feeling to the sound
And it can get artistic very easily
So what it would do
Here
On our signal is it would detect
The transient of our synth
And with some delay
It would turn the signal down
So the transient would pass through
And then we get some turning down
And then once
We're in the body of the sound
It would turn back up a bit slowly
Yeah, let's use the envelope
So we're getting
A different kind of
Feeling
Depending on
So it changes the attack
Basically from
Hear it again
Now it's very plucky
Now it kind of spills over
I like the plucky one
And then
Let's have it
Go back up
After
Let's say
Let's say half a second
But not too much
Right now it's feeling
It's kind of pumping
It's kind of pushing down the sound
And letting it back up
I don't know if you notice
But that's one way
To help our synth
Come through in the mix
Ok, let's define
A lead synth pattern
So for the code pattern
We used
These things here
For the lead synth pattern
What I will be doing is defining
A macro
Um
Which
Adds a note
To the signal
So it will be
Using a note number
And a certain beat duration
What it will do
Is
If T is positive
And T is
Less than B
Times beat duration
Add
Elite synth
Of
What will be the frequency
The frequency will be Nfb
And time T
Moreover
We should make sure that the envelope
Goes back down to 0
So let's do a smooth step
No, sorry
NfNN
So we should define a smooth step
That goes back down after B
So it will be B times B
Ture
And it will be 1
100th of a second before
And it will be 0 afterwards
Right
And then what do we do
We say T minus equals
Big time speed tier
In order to
Skip to the next
Note
And return sig
So
So now
What should happen
If we can do
Let's say
We should play
How do we play a basic scale
A basic arpeggio
Well
Let's say AC
D
And A
This should play
And A minor arpeggio
Perfect
So it's super boring but
We're getting there
Let us
Let us define
An interesting pattern
With that
So now it's the moment when we get creative
And try to find a funny melody
I have one in my head right now
So it happens to repeat
Every 8 beats
Let's do max T0
Like the previous time to avoid
Having anything
With negative time
1.75
Beats
Of silence
At the start
But when it repeats
It might be playing some sound
At the start of the bar
Let's do that before doing the modular
And then we will be playing
Right
So this is the pattern
I've come up with
I've actually not listened to it yet
So I'm not sure if it actually works
But let's try that
And
Yeah, that's exactly
What I wanted
Like for the previous sound
Let's add
Some delay to it
One thing we can do
Is
This one
Like this
Have
Another version
With
0.75 beats
Of delay
And have a third one
With one and a half
Beats of delay
And
Which decrease in amplitude
Each time
So what will that sound like
Right, that's pretty nice
I think
We also need
To have some fake
Early reflections
So let me put
Something like
5 milliseconds of delay
And have this
Be
Like that maybe
Oh
Oh, it's not working
Recursive function called
Yeah
Excellent
I think that will be it
For today guys
I was really glad
You could follow up until the end
Don't hesitate to share it with me
If you're doing anything creative
Anything fun
With all these ideas
You can find the link in the description
For this very script
That we have been getting to here
And in the next episode
We will be having a look at some more
Instruments
That we can create
Using frequency modulation
And some tricks
We will be doing bass
Marimba
And I think another lead sound
So that then we will be
Equipped
To start
Creating a whole song
Until then
Take care